Guide to the Office of Black Church Studies records, 1968-2013 UA.19.05.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Office of Black Church Studies records
1968-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Office of Black Church Studies
UA.19.05.0001
3 Linear Feet
The Office of Black Church Studies was established as an initiative of the Duke Divinity School in the early 1970s. The office was created to support African American students and faculty in the Divinity School and sustain a specific curriculum on black preaching and the black experience with Christianity. There are materials related to African American churches, civil rights, and the status of African American students and faculty in universities across the country. Materials related to Martin Luther King, Jr.; Benjamin Chavis; Gardner C. Taylor; and Prathia Hall Wynn are included. Some items relate to black church studies at other academic institutions, non-profit organizations, and churches. The collection includes manuscripts, black-and-white and color photographs, digital images, and electronic records contained on compact discs. There are publications that predate the creation of the office.
Collection Overview
The Office of Black Church Studies was established as an initiative of the Duke Divinity School in the early 1970s. The office was created to support African American students and faculty in the Divinity School and sustain a specific curriculum on black preaching and the black experience with Christianity.There are materials related to African American churches, civil rights, and the status of African American students and faculty in universities across the country. Materials related to Martin Luther King, Jr.; Benjamin Chavis; Gardner C. Taylor; and Prathia Hall Wynn are included.Some items relate to black church studies at other academic institutions, non-profit organizations, and churches. The collection includes manuscripts, black-and-white and color photographs, digital images, and electronic records contained on compact discs. There are publications that predate the creation of the office.
Related Materials
Black Graduate and Professional Student Association Records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Black History at Duke Reference Collection, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Black Student Alliance Records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Department of African and African American Studies Records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Divinity School Records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Divinity School Reference Collection, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Office of Minority Affairs Records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Historical note
The Office of Black Church Studies was created as an initiative of the Duke Divinity School in the early 1970s. The office was created to support African American students and faculty in the Divinity School and support a specific curriculum on black preaching and the black experience with Christianity.
The Office of Black Church Studies assists the theological formation of seminarians by supporting the work of the faculty, especially those teaching and administering courses in black church studies; counseling black seminarians and prospective students; providing educational opportunities through events, lectures, and domestic and international field education. It also helps students of color gain the greatest value from their theological formation, while supporting all students in deepening communion across racial and cultural boundaries.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The Office of Black Church Studies records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in January, 2014.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Correspondence, Events, Committees and Organizations, Administrative Files, Articles and Publications, and Visual Materials. Correspondence is organized chronologically. Other series are primarily organized alphabetically.
Compact discs; Clippings (information artifacts); African American graduate students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Theological seminaries -- United States; Students, Black -- North Carolina; Photographs; Pastoral theology -- Study and teaching; African American clergy -- North Carolina; Blacks -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Theology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina; African American students -- North Carolina -- History -- Archival resources; African Americans -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; African American college students -- North Carolina -- Durham; African American college students; African American students -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social life and customs; Clergy -- Post-ordination training; African American preaching; African American Christian educators; Duke University -- History; Duke University. Divinity School -- History; Duke University. Divinity School -- Students; Duke University. Divinity School -- Faculty; Duke University. Office of Black Church Studies; Duke University. Divinity School; Duke University -- Administration; Taylor, Gardner C; Education, Higher -- North Carolina -- History; Chavis, Ben; Wynn, Prathia Hall; Duke University. Divinity School -- Lectures, seminars, etc. -- Symposium on Christian Missions, 1958; Duke University -- Curricula; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968
- Correspondence, 1972-2004 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence from 1972-2004, primarily related to administrative matters. Correspondence is from office directors, including Grant S. Shockley, William C. Turner, Jr., and Tiffney Marley. Correspondence is related to admissions, the creation and administration of the Office of Black Church Studies, and various administrative matters.
  - Correspondence, 1972-1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2004 and undated (Box 1)
- Events, 1972-2013 and undated; 2
  Series includes correspondence, publicity materials, and photographs related to events sponsored by the Office of Black Church Studies, primarily lecture series named for Gardner C. Taylor and Martin Luther King, Jr. Other major events include pilgrimages to South Africa and Haiti, sponsored by the office; memorials for affiliated individuals; and Christian education seminars. Materials are primarily from 1972 to 2013.
  - Christian Education Roundtable, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Conference on Black Church Studies in the Southeast, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Continuing Education seminars, 1972-1985 (Box 1)
  - Funerals and memorials, 1982-2004 (Box 1)
  - Gardner C. Taylor Lecture Series, 1975-1999 (Box 1)
  - Gardner C. Taylor Lecture Series, 2000-2005; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Gardner C. Taylor Lecture Series, 2006-2013 (Box 1)
  - Gardner C. Taylor Worship Workshop, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr., celebrations, 1974-2006 (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr., Lecture Series, 1974-2002 (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr., Lecture Series, 2003-2013 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous events, 1978-2007 (Box 1)
  - South Africa pilgrimage, 2004 (Box 1)
- Committees and organizations, 1971-2005 and undated; 3
  Series includes materials related to campus organizations that interact with the Office of Black Church Studies, the Black Seminarians Union, but also other student and campus organizations. The series includes rosters, meeting minutes, budgets, and organizational events, primarily related to the Black Seminarians Union. Materials are primarily from 1971 to 2005.
  - Afro-American Studies program, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Black Church Affairs file lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Black Church Studies reports and committees, 1973-1995 and undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Black Seminarians Union 30th anniversary, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Black Seminarians Union constitution, 1971-1998 and undated (Box 2)
  - Black Seminarians Union budgets, 1981-1991 (Box 2)
  - Black Seminarians Union minutes, 1975-2005 (Box 2)
  - Black Seminarians Union, miscellaneous, 1984-2005 and undated (Box 2)
  - Black Seminarians Union National Conference, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Black Seminarians Union officers, 1989-2005 and undated (Box 2)
  - Black Seminarians Union rosters, 1978-2006 (Box 2)
  - Divinity School Council minutes, 2004 (Box 2)
  - International Studies Committee, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Student Representative Association Files, 1993-1996 and undated (Box 2)
- Administrative files, 1972-2004 and undated; 4
  Series includes materials related to admissions and recruitment, course materials, bibliographies, and faculty and job posting files. The series also includes photographs and newspaper clippings related to Julian Abele, the architect of West Campus. Materials are primarily from 1972 to 2004.
  - Admissions and recruitment, 1972-2000 and undated (Box 2)
  - Bibliographies and book lists, undated (Box 2)
  - Black Ministers in the N.C. Conference lists, undated (Box 2)
  - Course materials, 1972-1993 and undated (Box 2)
  - Faculty files, 1984-2004 and undated (Box 2)
  - Job postings and descriptions, 1972-2004 (Box 2)
  - Julian Abele files, 1991 (Box 2)
- Articles and publications, 1968-2005 and unated; 5
  Series includes newspaper clippings, departmental publications, scholarly articles, sermons and addresses and unpublished drafts of materials written primarily by students or staff members of the office. Materials are primarily from 1968 to 2005.
  - Miscellaneous publications and drafts, 1968-2004 and undated (Box 2)
  - Newspaper articles and clippings, 1973-2000 and undated (Box 2)
  - Prayers, undated (Box 2)
  - Recipes, undated (Box 2)
  - Scholarly articles, 1996-2005 (Box 2)
  - Sermons and addresses, 1974 and undated (Box 2)
  - The Sojourner, 1982 and 1993 (Box 2)
  - Unpublished materials, 1984-2004 and undated (Box 2)
- Visual materials, 1990-1996 and undated; 6
  Series includes both physical photographs and compact discs containing photographs. Primarily includes photographs from Black Seminarians Union events, and "Pilgrimage of Pain and Hope," a 2005 event involving Duke students, faculty, and alumni visiting Rwanda and Uganda to explore the aftermath of the 1994 genocide in South Africa. Materials are primarily from 1990 to 1996.
  - Compact discs, undated (Box 2)
  - General photographs, 1990-1996 and undated (Box 2)
  - South Africa photographs, undated (Box 2)